<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Overview</title>
  </properties>
  
  
  <body>
    <section name="Introduction">
      <p>
        Loom is a micro-kernel designed and implemented on top of the 
        Apache Avalon Framework.  Please refer to the
	    <a href="http://avalon.apache.org/framework/">Avalon Framework</a> 
	    documentation for more information about the framework.
	  </p>
	  <p>
        Loom provides a number of facilities to manage the
        environment of Server Applications. Such facilities include log management,
        classloading, thread management and security. In the future it will
        conditionally support extra facilities such as central server management,
        server pools, and other facilities aimed at reducing the time to market. 
        The API defines a standard method of piecing together server components and 
        creating a server.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Documentation is coming">
      <p>
        Some of the information on this site is currently a bit out of date. We are
    working hard to fix this. If you come across any inconsistencies or have a
    problem, please don't hesitate to contact us through the mailing list. Thank
    you.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Guide to Loom">
      <p>
        This guide starts with an architectural overview of Loom. Then, we identify
    the different roles that typically exist in daily use of Loom. For each of
    these, we provide a basic guide. We finish with a complete example.
      </p>
        <subsection name="Target Audience">
          <p>
            This documentation is aimed towards people who:
            </p><ul>
          <li>wish to create applications that run within Loom</li>
          <li>wish to create components (blocks) for use within Loom</li>
          <li>wish to setup and administer Loom</li>
              <li>are interested in the design principles of Loom</li>
              <li>wish to develop code that will be incorporated into Loom</li>
              <li>wish to reuse Loom concepts in their own application</li>
            </ul><p>
          </p>
        </subsection>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Acknowledgements">
        <p>The JContainer Group would like to thank <a href="http://codehaus.org">Codehaus</a> 
        for supplying resources to host the project</p>
        
        <p>This product includes software developed by the Apache Software Foundation 
        (<a href="http://www.apache.org">http://www.apache.org/</a>).
        </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
