<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Guide - Creating a Server Application</title>


  <author email="peter at apache.org">Peter Donald</author>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <section name="Introduction">
      <p>
        This document will describe the process for assembling your first Server
        Application. There is a number of steps in creating a Server Application.
        These are;
      </p>
      <ol>
        <li>Select the blocks you wish to assemble.</li>
        <li>Write the config.xml file.</li>
        <li>Write the assembly.xml file.</li>
        <li>Write the environment.xml file.</li>
        <li>Package the component and related resources into a sar file.</li>
      </ol>
    </section>
    <section name="Select the Blocks to Assemble">
      <p>
        As a assembler it is your responsibility to select the particular Blocks
        required to build your application. You may aquire the Blocks from a number
        of sources depending on your resources. You may use the core Blocks supplied
        with Loom, contract someone to build the component or download the Block
        from an online repository.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Write the config.xml file">
      <p>
        Configuration data for blocks is stored in the config.xml file.
        For more detail on the format of config.xml see the
        <a href="../..//reference/config-xml-specification.html">specification</a>.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Write the assembly.xml file">
      <p>
        The next stage is to write the assembly.xml file. The assembly.xml specifies
        the instances of Blocks that are part of the Server Application. Each
        Block has a name. Each block may also have dependencies that need to be
        satisfied and this can be done via the 'provide' sub-elements. The
        provide element maps block instances from the Server Application namespace
        to the Block role namespace specified in BlockInfo files. For more detail
        on the format of assembly.xml see the <a href="../..//reference/assembly-xml-specification.html">
        specification</a>.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Write the environment.xml file">
      <p>
        The next stage is to write the environment.xml file. The environment.xml is used to
        configure the code-based security policy, log management and thread pooling.
        For more detail on the format of environment.xml see the
        <a href="../..//reference/environment-xml-specification.html">specification</a>.
      </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Create the sar file">
      <p>
        The sar file format is the standard distribution format of Loom Server
        Applications. It is a standard Jar file with a specific directory layout.
        The config.xml, environment.xml and assembly.xml file must be stored in
        <source>SAR-INF/</source> directory of the archive. All jar files, including
        both those that contain blocks and those that contain support classes
        should be stored in the <source>SAR-INF/lib/</source> directory.
      </p>
    </section>

  </body>
</document>
