<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
    <title>Management Guide</title>
        
        
    <author email="huw@apache.org">Huw Roberts</author>
  </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Introduction">
            <p>
                Management refers to how a running instance of Phoenix, along with
                its components, applications and blocks is supervised and manipulated.
                This guide covers the steps required to write management-enabled
                applications using Phoenix.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Overview">
            <p>
                Management in Phoenix is divided into two distinct areas.  The first 
                area is the the management metadata.  This is information about which
                applications, blocks and
                components should be managed, the operations and attributes
                to expose, and descriptions for each these to help guide the user.
                Each block and component
                stores this data in an 'MXINFO file' that is distributed along
                with the class files that make up Phoenix and the Phoenix-enabled
                applications.
            </p>
            <p>
                The second area is the Phoenix component that uses the
                MXINFO files to generate a user interface through which Phoenix
                and its applications are interacted with.  It is anticipated that a number
                of such interfaces will be developed.  The current implementation
                of the management component uses the MXINFO files to generate
                ModelMBeans that are then registered and exposed through a slightly 
                customized JMX implementation called  
                <a href="http://mx4j.sourceforge.net/">MX4J</a>.    
            </p>
            <p>
                Note that nothing about the MXINFO file is dependant on using
                JMX, and the block author does not need to know or care about
                how Phoenix, the application, and its blocks will be managed.  
                His/her responsibility is limited to creating an MXINFO file.
            </p>
            <p>
                The guide is broken into a number of sections, each
                covering a particular aspect of the management picture.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Organizing Structure for Management Data">
            <p>
                This section provides a conceptual overview of the elements that
                are used to represent management information within Phoenix.
                An understanding of these elements and their relationships is 
                essential for all users of the management functionality.
            </p>
            <p>
                <a href="structure.html">Structure</a>
            </p>               
        </section>
        <section name="Step-By-Step Walk-Through">
            <p>
                This section walks through the steps that are needed to make a
                block manageable.  The emphasis is on illuminating the process,
                it does not cover every feature or option.
            </p>
            <p>
                <a href="overview.html">Step-by-Step</a>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="MXINFO File Format">
            <p>
                Management meta-data is stored in MXINFO files.  This section 
                describes its structure, as well as the runtime requirements
                of the management agent.
            </p>
            <p>
                <a href="mxinfo.html">MXINFO Format</a>
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Using XDoclet Tags to Generate MXINFO file">
            <p>
                Instead of writing MXINFO files directly it is recommended that
                component and block authors make use of custom tags inserted 
                into the source code.  These tags are parsed using the 
                <a href="http://xdoclet.sourceforge.net/">XDoclet</a>
                engine to produce the MXINFO file.  This section describes
                how to use the feature.
            </p>
            <p>
                <a href="doclet-tags.html">XDoclet Tags</a>
            </p>
        </section>        
    </body>
</document>
