<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
      <title>Guide - Step by Step Overview</title>
      <author email="huw@apache.org">Huw Roberts</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Introduction">
            <p>
              This section gives a quick overview of how to go from a block's source code,
              to a managed object accessible in a management interface.  It discusses
              the role of actors at three different points in the
              life cycle of the application:
              during development, at start-up, and while running.
            </p>

            <subsection name="In Development">
                <p>
                  For a block to be manageable, the developer must provide an
                  MXINFO file along with the compiled code.  The easiest way
                  to do that is to insert a series of XDoclet tags
                  into the source file.  An example of how to use these tags follows.
                </p>
                <p>
                First, at the class level, the block must be tagged as manageable
                with @phoenix:mx-topic tag:
                </p>

                <source>
/**
 * Ftp server starting point. Avalon framework will load this
 * from the jar file. This is also the starting point of remote
 * admin.
 *
 * @phoenix:block
 * @phoenix:mx-topic name="ftpServer"
 * @phoenix:service name="org.apache.avalon.ftpserver...
 */
public class FtpServerImpl extends AbstractLogEnabled
...
                </source>
                <p>
                  Then, for each attribute that should be exposed add the
                  @phoenix:mx-attribute tag:
                </p>
                <source>
    /**
     * @phoenix:mx-attribute
     * @phoenix:mx-description Returns the top published directory
     * @phoenix:mx-isWriteable false
     */
    public String getDefaultRoot() {
    ...
                </source>
                <p>
                and finally for each operation add the @phoenix:mx-operation tag:
                </p>
                <source>
    /**
     * @phoenix:mx-operation
     * @phoenix:mx-description Returns port that the server listens on
     */
    public String getServerPort(Integer instance) {
    ...
                </source>
                <p>
                    When this is compiled the LoomDoclet task extracts this and inserts it
                    into an mxinfo file.  If a method doesn't have a @pheonix:mx-attribute tag it is not exposed for
                    management.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Here's what the entry generated from the tags above looks like:
                </p>

                <source>
&lt;?xml version="1.0"?>
&lt;!DOCTYPE mxinfo PUBLIC "-//PHOENIX/Mx Info DTD Version 1.0//EN"
                  "http://jakarta.apache.org/avalon/dtds/phoenix/mxinfo_1_0.dtd">

&lt;mxinfo>

    &lt;topic name="ftpServer" >

      &lt;!-- attributes -->
      &lt;attribute
        name="defaultRoot"
        description="Returns the top published directory"
        isWriteable="no"
        type="java.lang.String"
      />

      &lt;!-- operations -->
      &lt;operation
        name="getServerPort"
        description="Returns port that the server listens on"
        type="java.lang.String"
      >
        &lt;param
          name="instance"
          description="no description"
          type="java.lang.Integer"
        />
      &lt;/operation>

    &lt;/topic>

&lt;/mxinfo>

                </source>

                <p>
                    Alternatively, you could write the mxinfo file directly (particularly in cases
                    where you can't/don't want to modify the source code).
                    The DTD is called 'mxinfo.dtd' and is available in the /src/schema
                    directory of the source.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="At Startup">
                <p>
                    At startup, Loom registers each block to a local SystemManager context.  This
                    context determines where the block fits into the management hierarchy.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The following code snippet shows the code snippet that registers
                    the Embeddor component with the 'component' management context.  A
                    similar process is followed for registering the blocks in
                    the application.
                </p>
                <source>
// get the management context
final SystemManager componentManager =
    systemManager.getSubContext( null, "component" );

// register the component
componentManager.register( ManagementRegistration.EMBEDDOR.getName(),
                           this,
                           ManagementRegistration.EMBEDDOR.getInterfaces() );
                </source>
                <p>
                    The system manager uses the mxinfo file in conjunction with introspection to
                    generate a ModelMBeanInfo object for each topic.  A RequiredModelMBean is then
                    created and exposed for management.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="While Running">
                <p>
                    In the default configuration, management is provided through MX4J.  The administrator can perform various
                    tasks such as deploying, starting and stopping applications and changing the configuration of various
                    blocks.
                </p>
                <p>
                    By default, the server is accessed on port 8082 of the server. eg. http://localhost:8082.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
