<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Management Guide - Organizing Structure</title>
        <author email="huw@apache.org">Huw Roberts</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Introduction">
            <p>
        Loom Management separates the information on what should be managed
        from the implementation of the management agent.  In order to maintain
        this separation, yet still allow the management interface to be rich
        and structured enough to be useful, it is necessary to impose an organizing
        strucuture on the management metadata.  This structure will be common
        across all management interfaces, although the specifics of how it is
        exposed is up to the implementor.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Elements">
            <p>
        Management information is stored in a structured format that contains both a
        functional definition of the actions (what can be done) and descriptive information
        about the actions (to help guide the user).  It is composed of the following elements:
            </p>
            <subsection name="Context">
                <p>
          In Loom, each managed object belongs to a single Context
          The Context contains a list of managed components called Targets.  In
          addition to the list of Targets, a Context can also have zero or more
          sub-Contexts.
                </p>
                <p>
          This nested structure of Contexts is the principal
          organizing element for management data, and is the bridge between
          the management code embedded in Loom and the implementation of the
          management component.  It is represented by the
                    <code>org.codehaus.loom.interfaces.SystemManager</code>
          interface.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Target">
                <p>
          A target is a manageable object.  Examples of Targets in Loom include the
          components, the applications and the blocks.  Each target has one or more topics.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Topic">
                <p>
          A topic is a logical grouping of attributes that can be get and/or set on the Target and a
          group of operations that can be called on it.  It is intended that Topics group together
          a particular aspect of Targets manageability.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
        <section name="Hierarchy">
            <p>
    This diagram illustrates how this might be presented in a management GUI:
            </p>
            <source>
Loom
 |
 +--Components
 |   +-- Kernel
 |   +-- Deployer
 |   +-- etc.
 |
 +--Applications
     +-- Hello World
     |    +-- Blocks
     |          +-- Block 1
     |          +-- Block 2
     |
     +-- Another App
          +-- Blocks
                +-- Block 1
                +-- Block 2
            </source>
            <p>
        In this example Loom, Components and Blocks are Contexts.  Kernel, Deployer, Hello World, Block 1, etc are Targets.  Each Target will then have one or more Topics.  Topics might be Logging, Lifecycle, Deployer, etc.
            </p>
            <p>
        In a jmx environment each topic would most likely be exported as its own mbean
        (so in the above example the jmx name would be 'Instance=Loom,Application=Hello_World,Block=Block_2,Topic=Logger'.
            </p>
            <p>
        In a swing environment each topic might have its own tab.
            </p>
            <p>
    In a command line environment, the syntax might be:
            </p>
            <source>
phoenix-mx.set( "Loom/Applications/Hello World/Logging/LogLevel", "DEBUG" );
phoenix-mx.describe( ""Loom/Applications/Hello World/Logging/LogLevel" );
            </source>
            <p>
        Again, the point behind the 'Organizing Structure' is to keep the management specification
        separated from the  management agent, while at the same time providing enough definition
        to keep a shared conceptual view between the two areas.
            </p>
        </section>
        <section name="Management Proxies">
            <p>
        There is one remaining concept to cover, the proxy.  It is a class that can be used
        to wrap access to the underlying target.  Posible uses include the mapping of data
        types to a more friendly type, (eg. from Date to String and back), cleaning up method names,
        providing backwards compatibility with older versions, and exposing methods
        missing from the target class, but available to it via a reference.
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
